Hi. Welcome to Teardown Tuesday.
Where is it? Is it up my sleeve? No,
it's on my shirt here. Well, not
actually this. This is just the uh
little microphone for it. What we're
going to teardown is the Sennheiser G3,
it's called, wireless microphone uh for
camcorders and other gear. It's pretty
much the ducks guts in the industry for
wireless microphones. Real expensive bit
of kit. Goes for over uh $600 or
thereabouts. Now, um I have had Well, I
do have wireless uh microphones in the
past. I've used a an Azden brand and
they were really crap. And then I
switched to this Audio-Technica Pro 88
and
uh it's kind of done the job for a few
videos, but it doesn't have a proper and
proper uh diversity receiver on it. And
well, everyone raves about this. This is
the number one in the industry,
apparently, the Sennheiser G3. Uh so, I
thought we'd take a look inside not only
the uh belt clip uh receiver here uh
sorry, the transmitter, but also the
receiver, which is on top of my camera.
Let's go.
And yes, sorry, I do already have it uh
powered on here and I'm actually still
using it to record. You can see this
cable. This is actually going from the
receiver here, the diversity receiver,
up to my
um Canon HFG10 camcorder here. And
you'll notice that it had a nice little
uh fade out backlight there on the
display. And this thing just oodles
quality from the moment I took it out of
the box. These things feel like, you
know, these things weigh and feel like
they're built like a brick dunny. They
really do. It weighs probably twice as
much. This is the uh transmitter here.
Uh you know, look at my old
Pro 88 here. It's It you know, this
thing probably weighs like twice as much
and is half the size because it's um
built with a diecast um alloy case on
it. And it's just ah it really is just a
beautiful bit of kit. Opens up like
this. This is not a review. I really
just literally taking it out of the out
of the box before I decided to do a
teardown here. So, I don't even know how
to use it properly, but it's all like
programmable graphic display. It's got
battery indicators. Fantastic. Runs on
standard double A's for like 8 hours or
something like that. It's got I think,
you know, dozens and dozens of channels.
It can do auto searching and auto
syncing and all sorts of weird and
wonderful stuff like that and you can
actually set
the one thing I really like is that you
can set not only you can set the
sensitivity here in DB on the
transmitter for the mic level, but you
can also do the same thing over here on
the audio frequency out that goes into
the camcorder. Minus 24 DB. So, full
flexibility there in terms of actually
you know, using this thing and setting
up for your camcorder. I love the little
battery door that clicks in place like
that.
Really is a nice bit of kit. I love it
and it does come with
the camcorder shoe attachment thing as
well. This is the SK 100 body pack
transmitter. Effectively known like as
the G3. Nobody calls it the
you know, the 100 or whatever and the EK
100 diversity receiver property proper
diversity receiver design so that you
know, it doesn't uh drop out like the
other crap ones do and things like that.
So, absolute first class
RF quality. Designed in Germany,
assembled in the USA and disassembled in
Australia.
Beauty.
Other thing I really like is the proper
threaded 3.5 mm TRS jack on these things
so they can't accidentally come out.
Many times I've um, accidentally plugged
my mic in, you know, halfway and I was
getting something on the LCD but it was
picking up crap loads of 50 hertz hum
and things like that. And it just really
is quite nice, nice little flexible
antenna there on the thing. So really,
you know, impossible to break these
suckers pretty much. And a mute and a
mic button there. Nice. And I do believe
they can take rechargeable like you can
get the cradles or something cuz they
look like a recharger uh, tabs to me if
you put rechargeable batteries in the
thing. And as I said, just feels first
class that die die cast alloy case just
fantastic and the quality of the battery
contacts and the
the hinge and the whole the whole works.
It just feels like you're getting your
money's worth. It really does. And this
is a UHF model of course better than the
lower frequency VHF ones which I've I
used before. This particular one is 626
to 668 megahertz. I'm not sure if it
changes in different regions. This is
the Australian model so it may actually
differ in that respect. So it looks like
we've got some torques screwdrivers
here. Designed in Germany of course so
I'm going to use my made in Germany Weha
screwdrivers. It's curious that the
Germans outsource to the USA.
Hilarious. Anyway, let's crack this
sucker open and see what's in it.
Hopefully we'll be able to get in with
just these
four screws here perhaps. We'll see. I'm
of course not
I switched my internal mic on my Canon
camcorder
of course as I do for most tear downs.
But if this thing works really well I
might use it more for the
more for just general purpose in the
blog but generally I got it for field
use. So let's whip these screws out.
Now, I expect first class uh, quality
design and build quality in here in
here. Maybe some RF shielding, although
it's the diecast case on the thing. Hey,
that's that's popping open real easy.
It'll be all SMD, of course. And
there it is. Look at that.
Ah, beautiful. The whole thing just
hinges out. The whole case. Ah,
fantastic. You can see the uh
Listen.
There we go. Nice diecast alloy case.
Beautiful. Ah, and that looks like basic
two-board construction. Don't know if
they might No, I think No, there's a
ribbon cable connecting fine-pitch
ribbon connecting the two boards. The
LCD's probably mounted on the back side
of that one though, I'd say. But uh that
is looking very nice right off the bat.
I rather like that. And of course,
they're threaded metal insert uh screws
right down into the uh molded and uh
then tapped uh threads in the diecast
case there. Just beautiful quality. Ah,
I love it. And it's all sort of hinged
on the one point. There it is a bit
loose like that. But of course, once
it's all uh screwed in, it's going to be
rock solid. But that's very nice. And
there's the RF board like that. Just two
metal uh cans with the uh some surface
mount circuitry on the back. The antenna
is soldered directly onto the board like
that. So, it just pops out and hinges
open in one fell swoop like that. That
is just beautiful design. No problems at
all. No signs of any bodges or anything
like that yet. So, ah, it's looking
beautifully designed. And you'll notice
that uh side charging contacts there.
Just you know, folded right angles and
soldered directly into the board. Really
quite beefy. Excellent. And on the back
of the main transmitter board there, no
surprises for finding an Analog Devices
ADF4117.
That's a 1.2 GHz phase-locked loop. And
that generates the local oscillator
frequency for all for the transmitter.
It's a digital interface device, a
serial interface. So, that's how the
microprocessor in this thing can select
the required frequency. Just
send the serial command to choose your
local oscillator frequency. Too easy.
And there's our antenna output over
there, you can see. And look at that
little puppy. Nice little distributed or
part of a distributed element filter
going on there. Pretty much just
basically coming out of there. Not sure
what you know, that's probably the RF
output power transistor or something
like that. Not going to decode those
SOT23 devices or anything like that.
But yeah, there's not much else on
there. Probably some local regulation
around here. They're going to have the
crystal oscillator associated with that
PLL as well somewhere. I'm not sure
where that is. Actually, I can't see the
oscillator down in there. Is that like a
little
That maybe looks like a little choke
there. I think that might be a little
common mode choke between
those things. But yeah, just some power
regulation. Got some big tantalums on
there for some huge bulky coupling. And
well, not a huge amount more. There's
going to be more in the RF cans on the
other side. One thing you will notice is
all of these test pads here, all around
here. These are for production level
testing after they've assembled the
board. Of course, they've got a bed of
nails tester which this thing would be
plugged into. Makes contact with the
pogo pins and does all of the RF testing
for this thing. Which you know, would
not be easy. Some real expensive
production RF test gear there, I'm sure.
And that's inside one of the cans there.
Not a huge amount happening. Once again,
I'm not going to decode those uh little
uh SOT23 type uh devices in there, but
you know, probably some RF uh
transistors or something like that.
Little four-pin package. You don't see
that uh very often, that's for sure. And
just one uh six-pin SOT23 and a whole
bunch of passives. And not a huge amount
under the other RF can, but we do have
ourselves a nice big wirewound inductor
there. Look at that puppy and some tiny
little um SMD inductors and things like
that. So, yeah. Not a huge amount. You'd
have to really get the uh schematic um
uh proper to know really what's going on
here. And we'll have a look at what I
call like the main uh processor kind of
board. Check this out. What we've got is
that a 4051. There you go. You've got to
have some uh 4000 series uh CMOS mux in
there, that's for sure. And right here
is a pretty uh critical component for a
high-quality wireless mic like this, on
semiconductor SA575.
And that's a uh dual-channel uh
compander. Well, one channel is a
compander, the other channel you can
configure as a compander, a compressor,
or an auto-level uh gain controller. So,
really versatile uh chip for um
you know, uh getting maximum dynamic
range out of your audio signal. Awesome.
So, a compander is basically a combined
uh compressor and expander uh circuitry.
And they're doing that to uh get the
maximum use out of the uh available
dynamic range of this thing. Pretty
critical in these microphones so that
they're basically uh going to
automatically bring up the uh low-level
stuff, but there's an art in doing that
without amplifying the noise and and
compressing some of that uh high stuff
and things like that. So, I I didn't
think this one actually did In the
reviews I read, didn't actually uh
mention that it had any um sort of
aggressive uh
compression or you know, dynamic range
compression or anything like that. So,
yeah. Not exactly sure how they
implement it in here and how aggressive
it actually is. Up there we've got a
Japan Radio Corp JRC 4580, pretty jelly
bean sort of op-amp, nothing much going
on there. Once again, probably lots of
channel and maybe some local regulation
stuff like that. It looks like probably
that might be part of the battery
switch my or the charging circuitry
linear technology charging circuit given
that it's right near the chargers there.
There we go, going through an input
diode and into there. So, that's
probably part of that charging stuff and
uh not much else happening on top here.
We can't find
the main processor. It's not there.
There's another 4051
marks, but yeah, that's uh
main processor must be under the bottom
there. Not sure what that one is. It's
uh not branded with anything familiar.
So, I don't know. I'm going to pop the
board out. And look at that, the whole
thing just swings out once again. That
is just absolutely beautiful
product design. I love that. They've
thought about how they're going to you
know, not designed for servicing really,
but you know, almost like it is back in
the old days. I'm not sure that they
service these at component level, but
that's just beautiful how it all goes
together and all in the one common hinge
point there. Oh.
And here's our main processor board.
Once again, we can't get access to the
processor, so it must be under the LCD
in there, just a chip on board LCD.
They've got the chip embedded in the top
there.
Uh we've got ourselves a crystal
oscillator there, another crystal
oscillator here, 4 MHz. We've got
ourselves some tactile
dome switches right on the PCB. Yes,
that is an infrared transceiver because
these things can actually talk to each
other via infrared to actually sync.
Fantastic. Nice little design touch
there. So, they actually know that
they're on the same frequency and you
know, the the receiver can know exactly
what the transmitter's on and vice
versa. Brilliant. Even the front panel's
all die-cast metal. Just gorgeous. And
you can see the backlight is just a
single LED there going into that light
pipe. And that's just fantastic. Very
nice even light pipe from a single LED
like that. Very impressive. For those
playing along at home, that's the LCD
model number. And there we go. A fairly
beefy little processor in this thing for
what it's got to do. Really, it's an NXP
LPC 2364.
And that's a 72 MHz ARM 7 processor,
128K of flash. It's got all sorts of
peripherals built in, 10-bit ADCs and
10-bit DACs and PWMs and all sorts of
stuff. It's a lot more powerful than I
would have expected
for something like this. So, I don't
know. You've got to wonder what sort of
processing this thing is actually doing.
And of course, they're most likely not
running that thing at the full 72 MHz
capability of course. It you know,
that'd be probably gross overkill on a
product like this where battery life is
pretty paramount. But this is quite a
low power processor, very efficient in
terms of you know, number of MIPS per
watts. So, after the impressive little
transmitter there, let's take a look at
the receiver. And as I said, this is a
true diversity receiver. So, it
you know, if you're going to get a
wireless mic, the real proper ones have
diversity receivers in there. And what
that means it's just a
There's many different types of
techniques to diversity receivers. But
pretty much it just tries to eliminate
you know, multipath distortion and stuff
like that which can cause dropouts which
are really annoying on uh wireless mic
systems like this. And here we go. I
expect uh this to be a very similar
uh arrangement to what we had before, of
course. So, if we get that open here.
And of course, what we expect to find
The interesting thing about a diversity
receiver is that it's got to have dual
antennas. And of course, this only has
one antenna. So, you got to wonder where
the other one is. Hmm. I think we'll
find out shortly. Pretty sure I know
where it is cuz there's only one with
this diecast case, of course. It can't
be inside there. So, how can we have a
second antenna in this thing? Well, the
only other output here is the um AF jack
going across there. And I bet you your
bottom dollar that is going to be used
as our second antenna.
Now, if I can get this
apart. Whoop.
Yep. Oh, look at that. Same hinge
design. Beautiful. Aw, what a Bobby
Dazzler.
Aha! Yeah, I was right on the money.
Check it out. There we go. There's
another uh looks like another
distributed element uh there on the PCB.
And well, there's another one there. But
yeah, here's the main receiving antenna
and then the secondary one going up
there
through
a little wire that goes up to the
shield, the outside shield of the output
um cable which goes to your
uh to your uh video camera over here.
So, they are using that as the second
antenna. And that's how they get the uh
uh diversity
uh feature of this thing. And of course,
um you'll see some receivers that are
diversity. They will have uh you know,
two separate antenna uh you know,
usually one coming out here and one
coming out here separated by X uh
distance. And well, that's another
method to do it as well. A bit more
controlled than this one with just a
lead sort of you know, hanging out,
flapping around in the breeze there. But
still, that's obviously going to work
quite well as a diversity antenna
system. And just like before, we've got
our top RF board here. Not a shielded
can. Maybe there's a a can on the other
side, but I can't really
see it.
May not be, but anyway, here's our input
here. We've got maybe an input
amp over here or something like that.
Yeah, we've got some sort of uh
filtering happening around here. We've
got a huge big
tracer. Is that a ground plane there?
Obviously stitched down in there through
There's a little Sennheiser logo there
on the PCB. They've obviously got some
via stitching around here to reduce the
impedance of the internal layer. It's
obviously a multi-layer board. You can
see in here. You can actually see the
copper on the inner layers down in there
inside this thing. And yeah, so the via
stitching all around here. They're very
common in RF systems just to lower the
inductance of the ground plane and the
grounding system. Little ceramic
hybrid modules there. Not sure what
they're doing. Some sort of, you know,
RF device or something like that. I
don't know. A hey H. No idea. If
anyone's familiar with those, please let
us know. Once again, all the test pads
as well for the automated production
test system. No surprises for finding
the exact same ADF4117 in the receiver
as well. The PLL to get that local
oscillator frequency. And you can see
that connection tab much clearer here.
It's a real big fat wide one going over
to the
shield of the TRS jack there. And to get
this board out, I've had to desolder the
tab there on the TRS jack. And we've got
ourselves four metal cans under there.
Oh, brilliant. But once again, we're
probably not going to find a huge amount
interesting under there. There's the top
one, very interesting little eight-pin
sort of extended SOT23 package. It's not
I don't think it's a SOT23, but yeah.
With sort of like you know, power
um
uh you know, pins coming out either
side. Sort of double width. Very
interesting. And there's the antenna by
the way with the uh second diversity uh
pad over there which I desoldered and uh
coupled in. So, they've got yeah, one
headed off over to here which is the cam
we just looked at over there. And you
can see the filter in uh the surface
mount SMD inductors in there. And uh the
caps and all sorts of stuff. And under
this cam, not a huge amount uh
interesting. Another four-pin uh
you know, power type device under there.
But of course, this isn't a uh
transmitter. It's only a uh receiver.
So, that's interesting handsome. Uh nice
huge um SMD wire wound inductors there.
Aha, look at that. 230.303
MHz
um oscillator module there with a
uh no brand name uh chip. It's just got
41 27 there. So, that's rather in. And
then 32 uh 44 which doesn't look like a
uh date code. You know, it wasn't
manufactured in uh
uh 1944, that's for sure. And the fourth
can over here, just some more uh basic
stuff as well. Nice little uh potted uh
inductor. There you can see like uh four
turns on that sucker and uh that's about
it. But yeah, it's um just most
interesting that they've really uh gone
to town here. Really built and braces
stuff in terms of
uh you know, separating and shielding
each section. I mean, very impressive.
And no surprises for the same uh
compander chip we saw uh the uh
companion one in the transmitter. You
got to have one here on this side. And
uh there's another uh
JRC jelly bean op amp. And that looks
like another JRC op amp, probably a
TL062 equivalent. Not going to bother to
look that one up. And and a couple of
unpopulated
devices on this board though. So there
is there another model I haven't looked
offhand. I don't know if there's another
model there, but certainly some
unpopulated parts. There's a max 4581
analog switch. Nothing really special
about there. And that's about all she
wrote here. But on the other side we'll
probably find the same NXP processor.
Actually, the top side here is rather
interesting. Check this. I mean it's all
the same, you know, we've got our
infrared
transmitter, we've got our oscillator
there, two oscillators here, and our
single lead diffuser, and you know,
sort of the same stuff happening that we
had before, but interestingly, it looks
like we have some sort of
interlock
switch here
and
over here as well. Check it out. Now at
first I thought it was like a door
switch, you know, to make sure the
battery door is actually
locked in position like that, but it's
you know, it doesn't make contact with
that battery door there. So it's
certainly not that. And on closer
inspection, no, it's not a switch in
itself. It's just a surface mount spring
contact like that. Maybe some spring
contact grounding going to the front
panel. And yep, exactly the same NXP
processor on here. So yeah, no surprises
because you're going to reduce your bill
of materials. You use it on one, you're
going to use it on the other, even
though you may not need the same
capability in both. So that's the
Sennheiser G3 wireless microphone
system, and I am very impressed, as you
probably uh could tell, with the design
and build quality of these things.
Absolutely first class. The design of
the hinging construction and how that
all goes together, it's just beautiful,
first class quality uh components. So,
you certainly do get your money's worth
here. What is it? 600 bucks worth of
these things. You know, they're really
expensive, but hey, you can't beat
quality like this. It's just absolutely
fantastic. They're built like a brick
dunny. I reckon they'll last forever.
Fantastic. So, there you go. I hope you
enjoyed that uh teardown of this uh
Sennheiser, designed in Germany, made in
the USA, disassembled in Australia,
Sennheiser G3. If you want to discuss
it, jump on over to the EVblog forum,
and the links, as always, are down
below. And if you like the video, give
it a thumbs up, but the YouTube system
is just these days. Anyway, catch
you next time.